Guide to the Marcella Perry Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Marcella Perry Papers
1945-1989
1970-1985
02/2014-011
Perry, Marcella
5.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection contains materials related to Marcella Perry's work as a banker and politician between 1945 and 1985. The contents are broken up into two series: News, Events, and Correspondence; and Photos, Scanned Documents, and Scrapbooks. The sequencing is chronological and maintains the original structure created by Marcella and her family as closely as possible.
Biographical Information:
Marcella Ellen (née Donovan) Perry was born to James and Ellen Donovan in the Houston Heights in 1908. Her father, James, was the city attorney for the Heights prior to Houston's annexing of the city in 1918. In 1950, Marcella was appointed to the board of directors of Reagan State Bank in Houston, but prior to that, she was a noted dancer. In 1922, she graduated from Heights High School and debuted in New York at Greenwich Village Follies. Marcella married Glenn A. Perry in 1930 and established a dancing studio in Houston where she taught various forms of dance to children and young adults.
In 1973, Marcella was appointed by Houston city council to serve as the city's first female commissioner of the Port of Houston Authority. In that same year, Marcella was president of Heights Savings Association; board chairman of First Pasadena State Bank, and Almeda-Genoa Bank; director of Reagan State Bank. She also served on the board of regents for Texas Woman's University and was politically active for much of her life. Marcella was also an active member of the American Bank Women's Association and the American Revolution Bi-Centennial Commission for Texas. In 1999, Marcella passed away from natural causes.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Port of Houston Authority
Genre/Form of Material:
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Newspapers; Photographs; Scrapbooks
Personal Name:
Perry, Marcella
Topical Term:
Bankers -- Texas -- Houston; Businesswomen -- Texas -- Houston
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for Research
Physical Characteristics or Technical Requirements:
Digital archival materials can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room. Contact curator Vince Lee (velee@uh.edu) for more information.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains materials related to Marcella Perry's work as a banker and politician between 1945 and 1985. The contents are broken up into two series: News, Events, and Correspondence; and Photos, Scanned Documents, and Scrapbooks. The sequencing is chronological and maintains the original structure created by Marcella and her family as closely as possible.
Detailed List of Contents
- News, Events, and Correspondence
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains news clippings, correspondence, and event invitations related to Marcella Perry's work as a bank executive and port commissioner. Digital archival materials can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room. Contact curator Vince Lee (velee@uh.edu) for more information.
  - 1956-1962 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 1963-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 1965 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 1969 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1970 (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
  - 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - 1973 (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - 1974 (Box 1, Folder 13-14)
  - 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - 1977 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - 1978 (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - February 25th, 1979, MDP Bnai Speech: Audio CDs [digital] (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - "The Royal Caribbean: Puerto Rico" passenger guide, 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 1)
  - "The Royal Caribbean: Virgin Islands" passenger guide, 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 2)
  - Richard Nixon commemorative inauguration poster, 1972 (Ovs box 3, Item 3)
  - Houston City Magazine, September 1982 (Ovs box 3, Item 4)
  - "The Spotlight: Who decides what civic art should—or should not—adorn the city?", Houston Chronicle, February 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 5)
  - "Houston Grand Opera: Let Us Entertain You," Texas Magazine, October 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 6)
  - Copy of American Declaration of Independence signed by Houston companies, July 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 7)
  - "Marge Crumbaker," The Houston Post, June 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 8)
  - "Heights banquet honors Mrs. Perry," The Leader, April 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 9)
  - "Property values rising in Heights: Heights in motion," The Leader, April 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 10)
  - "There's Little Chance You'll Be Allowed to Forget This Birthday," Houston Chronicle, July 1977 (Ovs box 3, Item 11)
  - "Business Spotlight: Heights Savings Association," Herald Voice, May 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 12)
  - "Who Has Time to Save: How to Accomplish More by Working Under Hair Dryer or Conking Out in Car," Houston Chronicle, July 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 13)
  - "Heights Savings Association" ad, The Hempstead-Waller News, February 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 14)
  - "New Look For Houston Heights On 1974 Horizon," The Leader, December 1973 (Ovs box 3, Item 15)
  - "City offers no help: 1200 seedlings planted in Heights," The Leader, March 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 16)
  - "Welch will speak at Heights Assoc. banquet in April," The Leader, March 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 17)
  - "Heights Savings Association Opening At Klein," The News, August 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 18)
  - "Membership in Heights Assoc. tops 100 mark," The Leader, February 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 19)
  - "Timbergrove Manor Civic Club General Meeting—March 5th," The Timbergram, March 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 20)
  - "Signing in," The Woodlands Sun, August 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 21)
  - "Savings Official Projects Brighter Economic Future," The Woodlands Sun, November 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 22)
  - "WIC Brunch to Recall Glamour of '30s Stars", undated (Ovs box 3, Item 23)
  - "Officials pledge help in renewal of Heights," The Leader, January 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 24)
  - "Profits called secondary in restoration of Heights," Houston Business Journal, August 1974 (Ovs box 3, Item 25)
  - Framed photo of Ben Barnes and Marcella Perry, 1969 (Ovs box 3, Item 26)
  - "Texas Bank Goes to the ABA Convention," Tex Sez, September 1965 (Ovs box 3, Item 27)
  - "Women Bankers Here for Session," The Austin American, undated (Ovs box 3, Item 28)
  - "Bank Building in Heart of Pasadena Expected to Run at Least 10 Stories," Houston Chronicle, September 1960 (Ovs box 3, Item 29)
  - "Moving Day Comes Saturday as Bank Merger Gets Final Approval: Combined Bank Opens Monday," Pasadena Daily Citizen, December 1960 (Ovs box 3, Item 30)
  - "Heights Savings Assn. To Open New Home," The Leader, June 1962 (Ovs box 3, Item 31)
  - "Listen, My Son" poem, undated (Ovs box 3, Item 32)
  - "The Heights In the Heart," The Houston Post, February 1967 (Ovs box 3, Item 33)
  - "We're Glad You Moved to Pasadena Texas' 14th Largest City: This is Pasadena," The News Citizen, August 1969 (Ovs box 3, Item 34)
  - Marcella Perry's certificate of appointment to the Small Business Administration, January 1969 (Ovs box 3, Item 35)
  - Marcella Perry's certificate of appointment to the Speaker's Advisory Committee of Texas, October 1971 (Ovs box 3, Item 36)
  - North Harris County News clippings, October 1970 (Ovs box 3, Item 37)
  - "Avalanche of stars...space shuttle study...NASA angered," Houston Post, May 1970 (Ovs box 3, Item 38)
  - "Female Banker Stays Busy," Houston Chronicle, September 1970 (Ovs box 3, Item 39)
  - Marcella Perry's certificate of appointment to the Texas Woman's University board of regents, May 1971 (Ovs box 3, Item 40)
  - "Obligations Faced By Bank Directors," The Tulsa Tribune, May 1972 (Ovs box 3, Item 41)
  - "Women's Progress Held Tied to Men's Rules," American Banker, May 1972 (Ovs box 3, Item 42)
  - "Secretaries: And how they feel about working for a woman boss," Houston Post, April 1972 (Ovs box 3, Item 43)
  - "Heights Savings Waller Branch Passes 2 Million," The Hempstead-Waller News, April 1972 (Ovs box 3, Item 44)
  - "Bank Management Should Consider the Auditor an Essential Control Factor," American Banker, September 1972 (Ovs box 3, Item 45)
  - "Two-party system...", Houston Post, September 1972 (Ovs box 3, Item 46)
  - "On the Boulevard," Houston Chronicle, June 1972 (Ovs box 3, Item 47)
  - "The Heights: Memories Are Made of This," Houston Chronicle, April 1971 (Ovs box 3, Item 48)
  - "John A. Guinn: He Came And Stayed: Beginning 22nd Year As President of Texas Woman's University," The Denton Record-Chronicle, August 1971 (Ovs box 3, Item 49)
  - "Marcella Perry enjoys prestige of banking post," The Houston Post, October 1969 (Ovs box 3, Item 50)
  - Souvenir Edition Celebrating the 50th Anniversary of First Pasadena State Bank, July 1969 (Ovs box 3, Item 51)
  - "Additional Federal Aid Now Being Given Cities," The News Citizen, October 1969 (Ovs box 3, Item 52)
  - "Pasadena is Proud of The World’s Largest Motor Bank!", The News Citizen, October 1969 (Ovs box 3, Item 53)
  - "Motor Bank Opening Is Saturday, 8:45," The News Citizen, October 1969 (Ovs box 3, Item 54)
  - "Mrs. Perry Gets Civic Award," The Leader, March 1967 (Ovs box 3, Item 55)
  - "Lower Bond Interest Rate Hoped For," The Daily Citizen, August 1960 (Ovs box 3, Item 56)
  - Invitation to First Pasadena State Bank's Grand Opening, May 1969 (Ovs box 3, Item 57)
  - "The Heights Is Sprucing Up for a Celebration," The Houston Chronicle, September 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 58)
  - "G.W. Hawkins Day in Heights," Houston Chronicle, September 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 59)
  - "Her Guideline: 'Just Raise The Money, Marcella'," Houston Chronicle, December 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 60)
  - "Heights fete honors city founder, auto," Houston Post, September 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 61)
  - "$9 million needed for parks projects," Houston Post, December 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 62)
  - "The Spotlight" column, Houston Chronicle, July 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 63)
  - "Port plenty big, plenty busy likely to near record in '75", The Houston Post, January 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 64)
  - Deer Park Progress clipping, May 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 65)
  - "Dallas Center ceremonies dedicate major addition," The Daily Lass-O, November 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 66)
  - "Reagan Bank celebrating its silver anniversary," The Leader, May 1975 (Ovs box 3, Item 67)
  - "Marcella lends French flair to charity affair," Houston Chronicle, January 1983 (Ovs box 3, Item 68)
  - "Super Texans," The Houston Post, March 1983 (Ovs box 3, Item 69)
  - "Donovan Park dedicated in Heights," The Leader, April 1984 (Ovs box 3, Item 70)
  - "Denton’s Young Lady Flexing Her Muscles," Record-Chronicle, December 1973 (Ovs box 3, Item 71)
  - "War Ends as Japan Bows to Surrender Demands: Cease Fire Call Issued: MacArthur to Take Foe's Capitulation," Houston Post, August 1945 (Ovs box 3, Item 72)
  - "These Are Pasadena State Bank Officers," The Pasadena Eagle, July 1954 (Ovs box 3, Item 73)
- Scanned documents, photos, and scrapbooks
  This series contains scrapbooks, photo sheets, and items from the folders Marcella's family labeled "Scanned Documents."
  - Scanned Documents
    - 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1964 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1966 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - 1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Photos
    - 1981 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - undated (Box 4, Folder 8-10)
  - Scrapbooks
    - 1980s Scrapbook Pages, 1980-1989 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - 1970s Scrapbook Pages, 1970-1974 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Scrapbook, 1975 (Ovs box 5, Item 1)
    - National Conference of Christians and Jews 29th Annual Brotherhood Awards Dinner, March 1977 (Ovs box 5, Item 2)
    - Scrapbook, 1974 (Ovs box 5, Item 3)